A Guide to the Governor James Monroe Executive Papers, 1799-1802
Library of Virginia
Governor Wood corresponds often with Samuel Shepard, Auditor of Public Accounts, and William Berkeley, Treasurer, regarding various financial matters. Shepard regularly encloses accounts of expenses for forwarding notices, executions, etc. (1800 April 19, 1800 Sept. 6, 1800 Nov. 8, 1801 April 11, 1802 April 10, & 1802 Sept. 3). On 17 Jan. 1801, Shepard provides a list of counties where there is no Collector of the Public Taxes. Additionally, John Carter, Clerk of the Auditor's Office, submits lists of warrants issued through the Auditor's Office (1800 Feb. 10, 1800 April 30, 1800 Aug. 9, 1800 Oct. 10, & 1801 Aug. 7). As Treasurer, William Berkeley regularly communicates reports and balances of specie in the Treasury (1800 Feb. 24, 1800 March 1, 1800 July 5,12,19, & 26, 1800 Dec. 23, 1801 Jan. 31, 1801 March 21, 1801 May 9 & 16, 1801 June 13, & 1801 Aug. 29). On 11 Feb. 1800, Berkeley encloses a letter from Edmund Randolph, in the absence of the Attorney General, regarding tobacco burned in one of the warehouses in Petersburg (1800 Feb. 11). In another letter, dated 14 June 1800, Berkeley writes concerning the establishment of a guard at the Capitol. Following Gabriel's Insurrection, Berkeley managed the discharge of claims for executed slaves. He writes on 31 Dec. 1800 that the sum for these claims is exhausted and will be increased by the late insurrection. On several occasions, Berkeley advises the Governor on the sale of the public tobacco in the Treasury (1801 Jan. 16 & 1801 May 2). The bonds of William Berkeley as Treasurer can also be found in these papers (1799 Dec. 31, 1801 Jan. 7, & 1802 Jan. 6).
Governors from other states comprise a significant amount of correspondence received by the Governor. This correspondence mostly relates to extraditions and the exchange of laws. Included are letters from the following governors: John Drayton, Governor of South Carolina; Ben Ogle & John F. Mercer, Governors of Maryland; John Jay, Governor of New York; Benjamin Williams, Governor of North Carolina; Thomas McKean, Governor of Pennsylvania; James Garrard, Governor of Kentucky; John Sevier & Archibald Roane, Governors of Tennessee; Caleb Strong, Governor of Massachusetts; Joseph Bloomfield, Governor of New Jersey; and John Trumball, Governor of Connecticut. John Drayton writes regarding the delivery of Elijah Hill for horse stealing (1800 Feb. 24); the transmission of South Carolina laws passed in 1799 (1800 May 5); and information on the negro insurrection in Virginia in order to prevent a similar conspiracy in South Carolina (1801 Sept. 27). Ben Ogle encloses a letter from Governor Richard Basset of Delaware regarding the negroes convicted in Southampton County (1800 April 26). Subsequently, his successor, John Francis Mercer, encloses a resolution passed to incorporate a company for establishing a turnpike road (1801 Dec. 31) and requests the requisition of Newell Walton (1802 Aug. 13). Benjamin Williams transmits a resolution (1801 Dec. 26) and a copy of public acts (1802 March 8). On 3 June 1800, John Jay discusses the regulations of the Penitentiary in New York and advises the Director of the Penitentiary in Virginia to visit the prisons in New York & Philadelphia. Thomas McKean writes concerning capital offenses and a pamphlet concerning crimes & punishments containing an account of the jail & Penitentiary House in Philadelphia (1800 June 16). James Garrard's correspondence relates to an act establishing the boundary between Virginia & Kentucky (1800 Dec. 27); a proclamation re. the capture of William Lamme (1801 Feb. 21); and copies of the acts passed at the last session (1802 Sept. 1). Both John Sevier & Archibald Roane write regarding the adjustment of the boundary line between Virginia & Tennessee and the meeting of the commissioners (1801 June 21, 1802 March 3, & 1802 Aug. 7). Lastly, Caleb Strong, Joseph Bloomfield, & John Trumball, transmit copies of acts, etc., from their respective legislatures (1801 May 8, 1802 Feb. 20, & 1802 June 18).
Additional significant correspondence includes the following: George Winston proposing to make bricks for the Penitentiary (1799 Dec. 9); Robert McCormick & Company proposing to furnish four thousand stand of arms to Virginia (1799 Dec. 30); James Swan re. the condition of arms furnished the Commonwealth in his first contract (1799 Dec. 31); Alexander Quarrier re. the enlistment of a sergeant & 5 privates for one month to guard the arms in the Capitol (1800 Jan. 21); James Latimer re. taking under his care the land belonging to the Commonwealth at Old Point Comfort (1800 Feb. 7); Charles Cox proposing to paint the Penitentiary (1800 Feb. 7); G.K. Taylor applying for the position of Attorney General (1800 March 5); Robert Pollard re. payment to James Swan for arms (1800 March 8,11, 18, & 29); John Cowper re. his appointment by the President as Vice Council for Sweden (1800 March 11); Andrew Dunscomb & Samuel Parsons, Acting Inspectors, encl. a copy of the minutes of the Board of Inspectors of the Penitentiary House (1800 April 26); William Hay & William Berkeley encl. a resolution that the Acting Inspectors of the Penitentiary be requested to cause the lower range of cells in the east end to be fitted up as dungeons for confining prisoners (1800 May 28); John Marshall re. his appointment by the President as Secretary of State (1800 June 7); J. Grammer to Augustine Davis re. a potential insurrection (1800 Aug. 9 ); Dr. James McClurg re. the intelligence received by Augustine Davis re. an intended insurrection (1800 Aug. 10); Edmund Randolph & Daniel Call re. filling up the stagnant pond on the Public Square (1800 Aug. 30); Mosby Sheppard re. intelligence of a slave insurrection led by Gabriel (1800 Aug. 30); Amos Alexander, Mayor of Norfolk, re. cases of yellow fever & the probably election of Thomas Jefferson as President (1800 Sept. 6); Amos Alexander re. proceedings for aiding the health officer & the Governor's proclamation re. Gabriel (1800 Sept. 13); James Taylor encl. a copy of a letter from Oliver Wolcott, Treasury Dept., re. the Marine Hospital (1800 Oct. 24); Edmund Pendleton, Jr., re. four of seven slaves committed to the jail of Caroline County for conspiracy based on the testimony of Ben Woolfolk (1800 Oct. 22); James McClurg, Mayor of Richmond, re. accommodating the Government with the corporation bell (1800 Dec. 3); Benjamin DuVal re. the necessity of patrols in Norfolk (1800 Dec. 26); Benjamin Stoddert, Navy Dept., to John Hopkins re. approval of the deed for conveyance of the Gosport lands to the United States (1801 March 3); Creed Taylor re. his acceptance of an appointment as Commissioner for Virginia to adjust the boundary line between Virginia & Tennessee (1801 April 25); John Miles presenting pistols to manufacture for the State of Virginia along with muskets & swords (17801 July 28); Creed Taylor re. the boundary line between Virginia & Tennessee (1801 Oct. 10); James Keith re. progress made by the Potomack Company in rendering the river navigable (1801 Nov. 13); William Foushee reporting on the James River Company and the improvement of the James River (1801 Nov. 26); Moses Bates re. the digging of the foundation for the Armory (1801 Dec. 2); James Tilton encl. extracts from the journals of the Senate of Delaware (1802 Jan. 17); Joseph Martin & Creed Taylor requesting another commissioner to settle the boundary between Virginia & Tennessee (1802 Jan. 26); Richard Jones re. an intended insurrection in Nottoway County & Petersburg (1802 Jan. 2); Moses Greer & John Prunty soliciting appointment as commissioners to run the boundary line between Virginia & Maryland (1802 Feb. 1& 2); Du Pont de Nemours re. Houdon statue of Washington (in French) (1802 Feb. 23); Thomas Mathews re. reports of an insurrection (1802 March 10 & 13, 1802 June 15); John Cowper, Mayor of Norfolk, re. inhabitants of the French islands who sought refuge in Norfolk along with their slaves (1802 Jan. 11); Creed Taylor re. the meeting to run the boundary line between Virginia & Tennessee (1802 March 27 & 29); John Clarke re. the broken bell formerly belonging to the Capitol proposing to be purchased by John Taylor (1802 April 8); John Cowper, Mayor of Norfolk, re. a rumored insurrection on Easter Monday, and the trial & execution of leaders involved in the conspiracy (1802 April 17 & 27, 1802 May 8, 1802 June 1); John B. Scott re. the trial of people plotting a proposed insurrection in Halifax County (1802 April 21, 23, & 30); George Goosley proposing to transport the slaves confined in the Penitentiary to either Surinam or Havana (1802 June 5 & 8); Christopher Gore, Commissioner to England, to Thomas Jefferson re. the emancipation of negroes for settlement in Sierra Leone (1802 Oct. 10); Saguaresa, Indian Chief, re. land belonging to the Pamunkey Indians (1802 Nov. 15); and Governor Monroe re. his retirement from office (1802 Dec. 7).
Other noteworthy items include: a report by Nathaniel Quarles & Jesse Bowles on the number of bricks laid in the Penitentiary (1799 Dec. 24); court proceeding of Southampton County of the slaves Sam & Hatter Isaac for the murder of Harris Spears & Joshua Butte (1800 Jan. 21); statement on the Tobacco Fund from 25 Nov. 1789 to 30 Sept. 1799 by Nathaniel Shepard (1800 March 4); schedule of guns examined & proved by Jacob Cooke (1800 March 29); report of Martin Mims & William Rawleigh re. the foundation of the tilt hammer forge at the Manufactory of Arms (1800 April 3); list of commissioners in each county for supervising the Presidential election (1800 July 29); proceedings of the Corporation of Richmond re. the infectious disease at Norfolk (1800 Aug. 28); return of election for electors in Norfolk County (1800 Nov. 5); list of electors appointed by the Governor (1800 Dec. 3); oath of Daniel Hylton as Clerk of the Privy Council (1801 Jan. 20); proclamation by Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of a slaves named Greenock (1801 Feb. 7); deeds from Philip Sheppard & Elizabeth Sheppard, etc., for the sale of slaves Pharaoh & Tom (1801 March 15); proclamation of Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of Isaac Venie (1801 March 16); proclamation by Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of John Anderson (1801 May 30); bond of Pickett, Pollard, & Johnson as agents to James Swan for the purchase of arms by the Commonwealth (1801 July 3); account of clothing delivered to the Public Guard including the names of officers & privates (1801 July 10); proclamation of Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of Peter Brookman (1801 Aug. 31); bills of lading for castings for the Penitentiary (1801 Oct. 21); list of arms distributed to the militia (1801 Nov. 13); schedule of the census for Eastern Virginia (1802 Jan. 20); proclamation by Governor Monroe for the apprehension of Isaac Farrow & Jacob Hersher (1802 Jan. 23); proclamation of Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of John Dunn (1802 Feb. 6); proclamation of Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of Obadiah Williams, Moses Burbridge, & Benjamin Sullivan (1802 May 20); report of the committee respecting the Penitentiary Building advising Clarke's alteration of the building by James Wood & William Foushee (1802 May 20); applications for the superintendence of the Public Tobacco Warehouse in Richmond (1802 June 7); proclamation of Governor Monroe for a reward for the capture of Thomas Gillespie (1802 June 7); proclamations by Governor Monroe for the apprehension of James & Mary Martin & John Franklin (1802 July 10); Commissioner's report on the state of the Treasury (1802 Oct. 2); return of clothing due the Public Guard (1802 Nov. 26 & 27); and an act concerning the title papers of lands in the forks of the Big Sandy from the Kentucky Legislature (1802 Dec. 22).
The Subject Files series contains subject files separated from Governor Monroe's Executive Papers related to three topics: Gabriel's Insurrection, the McCormick-Miles-Haslett Arms Contract, and Receipts for Pamphlets. Note that documents related to these subjects may still been found in the Chronological files. These files were originally separated to provide a ready-reference to researchers.
Gabriel's Insurrection was the most significant historical event during James Monroe's time in office. Included are court records, trials, condemnations, confessions, pardons, proceedings, and correspondence regarding the slaves involved in the conspiracy & insurrection led by Gabriel, the property of Thomas Prosser of Henrico County. Significant documents include: a letter from James McClurg, Mayor of Richmond, re. an intended insurrection (1800 Sept. 1); a letter from Joseph Jones warning of an intended rebellion of slaves, free negroes, and mulattoes (1800 Sept. 8); a resolution of the Common Hall of Richmond by Adam Craig re. an intended insurrection (1800 Sept. 9); Adam Craig, aid-de-camp to the Governor, requesting a temporary exemption from guard duty (1800 Sept. 13); a letter from Thomas Newton re. the capture of Gabriel on board the Schooner Mary and the conduct of its master, Richardson Taylor (1800 Sept. 24); a letter from Richard E. Lee, re. the arrival & apprehension of Gabriel in Norfolk (1800 Sept. 25); a letter from James Monroe to the Council re. the delivery of Gabriel to the Penitentiary (1800 Sept. 28); minutes of the Council re. the confession of Gabriel and advice that extra guard be dismissed (1800 Sept. 28); a letter from William Wilkinson re. an apprehended insurrection and the ordering up of part of the militia at Suffolk (1800 Oct. 1); and a letter from Thomas Newton re. accounts of an insurrection at Norfolk (1800 Dec. 29).
The McCormick-Miles-Haslett Arms Contract consists of correspondence, receipts, bills of lading, contracts, bonds, and other documents related to the contract between Robert McCormick & Company of Philadelphia, Pa., and the Commonwealth of Virginia for 4,000 muskets. McCormick sold his arms factory in May 1801 to John Miles who took over and completed the contract in 1803. General John Shee served as agent for the State of Virginia. Much of the correspondence, bills of lading, and receipts were sent by Shee in Philadelphia to Samuel Coleman in Richmond. There are also receipts from James Haslett, the superintendent of McCormick's works who continued employment when the factory was sold to John Miles.
Lastly, the Receipts for Pamphlets, are simply receipts from individuals who delivered documents from the Governor. The receipts provide the name of the recipient, the county, and the amount of miles traveled. In April 1800, Governor Monroe arranged for the delivery of reports of a select committee of the House of Delegates with copies of answers of several states to a resolution of the General Assembly of 21 December 1798 on the United States Alien & Sedition Laws. Other receipts document the delivery of dispatches to militia commanders and letters to Commissioners for Equalizing the Land Tax between August & September 1800.
Arrangement
James Monroe's Executive papers are organized into two series. Series have been designated for Chronological files and Subject files. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Chronological Files
  - 1799
    - December
      - 7-20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 21-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1800
    - January
      - 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 18-31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - February
      - 3-10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 11-27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 17-31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - April
      - 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - May
      - 2-15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - July
      - 1-12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 19-31 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - August
      - 1-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 21-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - September
      - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 11-20 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 22-30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - October
      - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 11-31 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - November
      - 1-10 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 11-29 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - December
      - 1-14 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1801
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - February
      - 2-15 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - 16-28 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - March
      - 3-15 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - April
      - 2-15 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - 18-30 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - May
      - 2-15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - June
      - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 11-20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 21-30 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - August
      - 1-14 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 20-31 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - September (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - October
      - 1-14 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Beaumarchais Case (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - November
      - 2-14 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 17-30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - December
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1802
    - January
      - 2-15 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - February
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - 18-28 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - April
      - 1-14 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - May
      - 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - 21-30 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - 16-29 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - 16-31 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - August
      - 2-14 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 16-31 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - September
      - 1-16 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 17-30 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - October
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - 16-31 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - November
      - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 16-29 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - December
      - 1-24 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Pardons
      - A-I (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - J-P (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - R-W (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - Gabriel's Insurrection (1800)
    - September
      - 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - October (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - November-December (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - McCormick-Miles-Haslett Arms Contract
    - 1800
      - April (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - September-December (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1801
      - January-June (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - July-September (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - October-December (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1802
      - January-February (Box 8a, Folder 1)
      - March-May (Box 8a, Folder 2)
      - July-December (Box 8a, Folder 3)
  - Receipts for Pamphlets, 1800 (Box 8a, Folder 4)
- Oversized (Clamshell Box)
  - 1800
    - Jan. 12 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 27 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Jan. 28 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Feb. 8 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Feb. 24 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - April 17 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - May 26 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - June 6 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - June 18 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - July 23 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Sept. 6 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Sept. 12 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Nov. 27 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Nov. 27 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Nov. 29 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Dec. 3 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - 1801
    - Jan. 17 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Jan. 20 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Feb. 28 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - April 28 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - May 24 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - May 25 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - May 30 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - June 8 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - July 3 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - July 22 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Oct. 22 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - 1802
    - Jan. 20 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Feb. 25 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - March 5 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - March 27 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - June 19 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Aug. 2 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Aug. 5 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Aug. 7 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Aug. 12 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Sept. 17 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Oct. 2 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Nov. 27 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Pardons (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Undated (Box 9, Folder 40)
- Oversized (Newspaper Box)
  - 1800
    - Nov. 5 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1801
    - April [N.D.] (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - May 25 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - June 15 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Oct. 29 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Nov. 12 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1802
    - Jan. 9 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 17 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Feb. 2 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - May 12 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Oct. 26 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Dec. 22 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Pardons (Box 10, Folder 13)